Lewis Varick Frissell Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Lewis Varick Frissell Papers 1917-1970 (bulk 1925-1931)
MSS55277
Frissell, Lewis Varick, 1903-1931
650 items
5 containers
2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Explorer and cinematographer. Correspondence, diary, drafts of writings, film scripts and other production materials, business papers, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and other papers relating chiefly to Frissell's explorations and the production of the films, The Great Arctic Seal Hunt (1928) and The Viking (1931). Later materials relate to Frissell's disappearance in a shipwreck while on location for The Viking and attempts by members of his family to ascertain and publicize the facts of his career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
England, George Allan, 1877-1936--Correspondence.; Flaherty, Robert Joseph, 1884-1951--Correspondence.; Frissell, Lewis Fox, 1872-1934--Correspondence.; Frissell, Toni, 1907-1988--Correspondence.; Frissell, Varick, 1903-1931.; Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940--Correspondence.
Organizations
Explorers Club.; Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain)
Subjects
Documentary films--Production and direction.; Motion pictures--Production and direction.; Rivers--Newfoundland and Labrador.; Shipwrecks.
Places
Arctic regions--Discovery and exploration.; Churchill River (N.L.)--Discovery and exploration.; Newfoundland and Labrador--Discovery and exploration.; Unknown River (N.L.)--Discovery and exploration.
Titles
Great Arctic Seal Hunt (Motion picture); Viking (Motion picture)
Occupations
Cinematographers.; Explorers.
Provenance
The papers of Lewis Varick Frissell, explorer and cinematographer, were given to the Library of Congress by his sister, Toni Frissell, in 1975.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Library’s Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Lewis Varick Frissell are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, Aug. 29 Born, New York, N.Y.
1920 Traveled to Newfoundland
1925 Explored Unknown River region of Labrador
1926 B.A., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1927 Filmed Great Artic Seal Hunt (released 1928)
1928 Elected member of Royal Geographic Society and Explorer's Club
1929 Filmed newsreel footage of Mexican Revolution
1930 Began to film, as producer, The Viking (released posthumously 1931)
1931, Mar. 15 Killed in shipboard explosion off the coast of Labrador
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lewis Varick Frissell (who was known throughout his life as Varick Frissell) span the years 1917-1970, with the greatest portion of the material dated 1925-1931. The diary, correspondence, writings, and business papers of these years reflect a short but intense career of arctic exploration, writing, and documentary and feature film making. Earlier papers are Frissell's juvenilia (mostly fiction), and later papers are those of his family. The collection is organized by type of material.
Frissell's expedition to the Unknown River region of Labrador in 1925 resulted in his discovery of the Lower Twin Falls of that river and in the first photograph of the Grand Falls on the Hamilton River (now Churchill River and Falls). The journey is documented in the diary, correspondence, and articles in the collection. This and subsequent explorations in Labrador earned Frissell election as a Fellow of the Royal Geographic Society and as a member of the Explorer's Club.
Much of the general correspondence and most of the business papers, as well as the scripts and related papers in the collection, pertain to the two feature films produced by Frissell. The Great Arctic Seal Hunt (1928), a silent documentary, was written, produced, and photographed by Frissell while he worked as a sealer off the Labrador coast in 1927. The Viking (1931), the first feature-length sound film produced entirely on location, was written and produced by Frissell and was directed by George Melford. The writings file in the collection includes synopses for both films and scripts, continuity notes, and a negative film record for The Viking. Distribution contracts and agreements, schedules of showings for both films, and copies of correspondence between third parties about these arrangements are included in the business papers.
In addition to the papers related to motion pictures, the writings contain numerous articles on Labrador and the Arctic, reflecting Frissell's interest in the promotion and development of the region. Other writings include Frissell's fictional pieces and his poetry.
The largest sequence of general correspondence is between Frissell and Sir Wilfred Thomason Grenfell and his philanthropic organization, the International Grenfell Association. Grenfell, with whom Frissell had stayed on his first and on many later visits to the North, was a well-known medical missionary to the Eskimos of Labrador. Other prominent correspondents are Robert Joseph Flaherty, the noted documentarist, and George Allan England, whose story "Vikings of the Ice" Frissell adapted for The Viking.
Family correspondence in the papers contains letters to and from Frissell and his father, Lewis Fox Frissell, regarding Frissell's plans for and experiences on his northern journeys. A large portion of the correspondence of Frissell's father relates to the search for Frissell that was instituted during the spring of 1931, after the ship on which he was retaking some scenes for The Viking exploded. Frissell was never found, but the search for him is closely chronicled in telegrams and letters, as well as newspaper clippings in the subject file and in scrapbooks.
The much later, 1965-1970, correspondence of Toni Frissell in the family correspondence reflects her attempts to ascertain and publicize the facts of her brother's career. Several of these letters contain enclosures that are copies of Frissell's correspondence with his lawyers and with the Royal Geographic Society.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Diary, written on bound-in interleaves of A. P. Low, Report on Explorations in the Labrador Peninsula (Ottawa, 1896), 1925 (Box 1)
- Family correspondence, 1925-1931 (Box 1)
  - A-G, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - H-Z and unidentified, (3 folders) (Box 2)
- Writings, 1917-1930 (Box 2)
  - Articles (Box 2)
    - "Explorations in the Grand Falls Region of Labrador" (Box 2)
    - "Flying South with Arctic Gales" (Box 2)
    - "To Grand Falls and the Unknown River of Labrador" (Box 2)
    - "In Darkest Labrador" (Box 2)
    - "Labrador and Another Niagara" (Box 2)
    - "Labrador as I Like It" (Box 2)
    - "A Niagara in the Heart of Labrador" (Box 2)
    - "Two Hundred Miles Down Newfoundland by Dog Team" (Box 2)
    - "Vast Treasure Lies in 'God's Dump Heap" (Box 2)
    - "What I Saw of the German Submarine U-53" (Box 3)
    - Untitled narrative of experiences during the Mexican Revolution (Box 3)
    - Untitled narrative of a sea voyage (Box 3)
  - Scripts and related papers (Box 3)
    - The Great Arctic Seal Hunt, synopsis (Box 3)
    - Viking of the Ice Fields (Box 3)
      - Script (Box 3)
      - Continuity notes (Box 3)
      - Picture negative record (Box 3)
  - Short stories (Box 3)
    - "Actors" (Box 3)
    - "Humgumption" (Box 3)
    - "One of Those Trivial Matters" (Box 3)
  - Poem, "So Often Have I Seemed a Puny Thing" (Box 3)
- Subject file, The Viking disaster (Box 3)
  - Documentation (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
- Business papers (Box 3)
  - General, 1928-1931, undated (Box 3)
  - Banking records, 1929-1931 (Box 3)
- Miscellany, 1927-1970 (Box 3)
  - Annotated lists of Frissell's writings and other papers (Box 3)
  - Biographical notes on Frissell (Box 3)
  - Film reviews (Box 3)
  - Memorial service and tribute to Frissell (Box 3)
  - Opinion cards for film White Thunder (Box 3)
  - Press clippings, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Printed matter, 1927, 1930-1968, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Writings by others, typescript (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, "Varick Frissell, Producer, The Viking" (Box 5)
  - Press clippings (Box 5)
- Oversize negative photocopies of articles about Frissell, Los Angeles Times and other newspapers (Box OV 1)